is there an optimal uh T2 E2
ratio I think that there probably is an
optimal ratio but I think the ratio is
very Broad and I think it encompasses a
very wide range of numbers um and that
ratio is going to self-regulate for men
who are healthy the issue that guys are
having when it comes to firstly when it
comes to libido libido is a very uh
multifactoral volatile and often
influenced by things outside of biology
it can be impacted by the relationship
it can be impacted by confidence it can
be impacted by work stresses so many
different things so sometimes it's very
normal for guys to not have much of of
libido regardless of where their
hormones are at because of their
circumstances um so that's something
that guys just need to wrap their head
around is that testosterone replacement
therapy is not just going to be a
bulletproof vest to give them a 16year
old's libido all the time um so when it
comes to what the optim estrogen level
is it's something that should if an
individual is healthy self-regulate the
factors that impact arates are things
like T3 uh insulin uh prolactin cortisol
and if there are factors that are
disregulated those parameters then
estrogen will become disregulated the
problem though is that estrogen is an
anti-inflammatory hormone it's a
protective hormone so in all of those
circumstances estrogen's the fire engine
it's not the fire we don't want to get
rid of the fire engine we want to put
the fire out so it's not estrogen's
fault per se estrogen is like the smoke
alarm going off we need to work out what
the problem is and address so but with
that said I I have not found that
estrogen levels correlate with estrogen
symptoms um in the context of trt at
least now if someone's estrogen is like
astronomically through the roof like you
know 200 or 300 or something like that
yeah okay different story but for GU for
the for the most part for you know 99.9%
of guys on trt estrogen should settle
where it's supposed to settle because we
can't measure things like you know uh
receptor availability um you know the
ratio between um Alpha and beta
receptors all of that kind of stuff we
can't measure so there's not a optimal
estrogen ratio but if someone is
troubleshooting their trt they need to
look at all the blood work overall
because a lot of the time there's you
know D like if there's libido issues
there can be a DHE deficiency they can
be hypothyroid um they can be
chronically stressed they can have other
factors leading to you know defic they
could be on SSRI anti-depressants there
is so many factors that these guys don't
disclose when they're troubleshooting
these things or their providers don't
look at so just trying to manipulate
testosterone and estrogen to solve a
man's problems we have seen how this
plays out it's why this group exists it
doesn't work
[Music]